A Guide to the Office of the President: Committee Records, 1909-1957: UA 0040
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Office of the President: Committee Records,
1909-1957
Special Collections, James Madison University
JMU Office of the President
UA 0040
.2 cubic feet; 1 box
The Office of the President: Committee Records, 1909-1957 is comprised of meeting minutes, correspondence, reports and budgetary information, documenting the work of various committees during the first 50 years of the State Normal and Industrial School for Women (subsequently known as the State Normal School, State Teachers College, and Madison College).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Present in the cage at the time of founding.
Administrative History
The State Normal and Industrial School for Women committee records from 1909 to 1957 document various efforts by faculty members and administrative staff to shape and regulate student life, found student publication and organizations, promote the school in the community, and influence the design of campus buildings and landscape.
Scope and Content
The Administrative Council papers contain correspondence regarding absences, illness and other attendance matters, and meeting minutes discussing student disciplinary matters, student regulations, senior class privileges, recommendations made by the Student Council (1:1).
The Alumnae Relations Committee minutes include topics such as the formation of the Rockingham Harrisonburg Chapter of the Alumnae Committee, membership association dues and planning class reunions. John Wayland was secretary (1:2).
The Committee for Student Welfare documents include regulations for boarding students, disciplinary matters, the formation of student government association in 1912, senior privileges, and a schedule of the churches that faculty members were assigned to attend. It contains boarding agreement forms and a document called, "Recommendations to the Literary Societies made by the Student Welfare Committee," given to the Lee and Lanier Literary Society. There is also a reference to Walker Lee, African American janitor and long-time employee at the school. Natalie Lancaster served as chair (1:2).
The Committee on Appointments and Relations to other Institutions document faculty speaking engagements in the community and at other institutions (1:3, 1:4).
The Committee on Equipment meeting minutes contain recommendations regarding the design and landscaping of campus; recommendations that teachers' accommodations be designed according to historic models such as the Mary Washington House in Fredericksburg, and "other of the less pretentious colonial homes of Virginia"; and specific items for purchase such as library books, hat racks, rugs and thermometers for classrooms. The committee was chaired by John Wayland. The Library Committee (1926-1940) is comprised of meeting minutes and budget recommendations (1:5).
Committee on Public Exercises and Entertainments Record book contains meeting minutes regarding the planning of movies, concerts, theater performances and other campus events for students. It includes budget information, and listings of entertainers that came each year. The committee was first chaired by John Wayland, followed by Bessie Lanier and Edna Schaeffer (1:6, 1:7)
The Committee on Publications meeting minutes outline the formation of the "Schoolma'am," and documents early editors, constitutions, contracts with publishers and fundraising efforts. The minutes also document the concerted efforts by the faculty to publish in educational journals, scholarly journals, and popular, regional newspapers. Minutes were submitted by Elizabeth Cleveland (1:8, 1:9).
The Committee on Student Publications documents are comprised of correspondence, reports, and budgets related to every day workings of "The Breeze" and "The Schoolma'am." It includes a report regarding the copper shortage during World War II (which impacted newspaper printing), travel plans for the Associated Collegiate Press Convention, correspondence with various printers, and student elections (1:10).
Arrangement
Folders are arranged by topic.
Separated Materials
Faculty meeting minutes from 1913-1927 were removed from the collection and added to UA 0007, Office of the President: Faculty Minutes, 1909-1998.
Index Terms
Subjects:
State Normal School for Women at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- History; State Normal and Industrial School for Women (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- History; State Teachers College at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- History; Madison College -- History; James Madison University -- History
Genre and Form Terms:
Minutes (administrative records); Letters (correspondence); Administrative reports; Telegrams; Minute books
- Administrative Council Papers, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Committee on Alumnae Relations and Student Welfare Committee, 1911-1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Committee on Appointments and Relations to other Institutions, Record Book, 1911-1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Committee on Appointments and Relations to other Institutions, Loose Inserts, 1909-1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Committee on Equipment and Library Committee, 1911-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Committee on Public Exercises and Entertainments Record Book, 1926-1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Committee on Public Exercises and Entertainments, Loose Items, undated-1956 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Committee on Publications, Minutes, 1909-1913 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Committee on Publications, Loose Items, 1911-1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Committee on Student Publications, 1940-1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)